Finding Aid for Loraine M. Gutiérrez Papers, 1973-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Loraine M. Gutiérrez Papers 1973-2007
Gutiérrez, Lorraine M.
2 linear feet
2012090 Aa 2
Professor of Social Work and Psychology at the University of Michigan with teaching and research interests in social work practice for the empowerment and organization of multicultural communities. The Lorraine M. Gutiérrez papers contain courses syllabi, papers, research proposals, and topical files
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor no. 10,235) were received in July 2009. NO.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The papers are open without restriction.
Lorraine Margot Gutiérrez received her A.B. in History from Stanford University in 1976 and her A.M. from the School of Social Service Administration at the University of Chicago in 1978. From 1979 to 1984, she worked with various social service agencies in New York including Domestic Violence Prevention and Victim Services Agency. Gutiérrez earned an A.M in Psychology from the University of Michigan in 1986 and her Ph.D. with a dual focus in Psychology and Social Work in 1989.
Gutiérrez joined the faculty of the University of Washington as Assistant Professor of Social Work in 1989. In 1994, she was promoted to Associate Professor. That same year, she came to the University of Michigan as a Visiting Associate Professor of Social Work. In April 1995, the Regents of the University of Michigan appointed Gutiérrez Associate Professor of Social Work in the School of Social Work with tenure and Associate Professor of Psychology in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts without tenure. In 2001, Gutiérrez was promoted to Professor of Social Work with tenure and Professor of Psychology without tenure.
Gutiérrez's involvement with students and the University of Michigan community has been extensive. She is the director of the Joint Doctoral Program in Social Work and Social Science. Since 1995, Gutiérrez has served as the Program Coordinator for the University of Michigan Detroit Initiative in Psychology. From 1998 to 1999, she was a Faculty Associate with the University of Michigan Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. Gutiérrez was nominated in 2000 to an Arthur F. Thurnau Professor, a professorship established to recognize faculty members for outstanding contributions to undergraduate education. She was reappointed to the professorship in 2006.
Professor Gutiérrez's research focuses on social work practice for the empowerment and organization of multicultural communities. She has published widely on the subject in books, articles, book chapters, and papers. She was selected by the American Psychological Association as the 2009 recipient of the Contributions to Interventions and/or Assessment for Communities of Color in Clinical Psychology Award.
The Lorraine M. Gutiérrez Papers are comprised of 2.5 linear feet of materials that cover the years 1973-2007. These materials primarily relate to the teaching and research interests of Gutiérrez, Professor of Social Work and Professor of Psychology. The collection is divided into four series: Course Syllabi & Evaluations, Papers, Proposals, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Gutiérrez, Lorraine M. (Lorraine Margot); Social work education.; Social group work.; Social work with minorities.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Course Syllabi & Evaluations 1994-2006
  The Course Syllabi & Evaluation series (1994-2006) is arranged alphabetically by course letter designation and then by course number. It contains syllabi, anonymous course evaluations, and documents from University of Michigan courses taught or co-taught by Professor Gutiérrez in the School of Social Work, Psychology, and Rackham Graduate School. This includes classes on the undergraduate and graduate levels. Most files contain at least a syllabus but there are differing levels of coverage.
  - Psych 305, fall 1996 (Box 1)
  - Psych 317/318 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Psych/AC 319, fall 2006 (Box 1)
  - Psych 470 1995-1998 (Box 1)
  - Rackham 570, fall 1998 (Box 1)
  - SW 501, winter 1995 (Box 1)
  - SW 531, winter 1998 (Box 1)
  - SW 560, fall 1994 (Box 1)
  - SW 650, spring 1998 (Box 1)
  - SW 651, fall 1999 (Box 1)
  - SW/UP 654, winter 2001 (Box 1)
  - SW 657 1995, 1998, 2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - SW 658, Spring/Summer 1999 (Box 1)
  - SW 697 1999-2004 (Box 1)
  - SW 742, winter 1998 (Box 1)
  - SW 800 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - SW 816 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - SW 818/978 1996, 1998, 2000 (Box 1)
  - SW 837/Psych 808, fall 1999 (Box 1)
- Papers 1986-2003
  The Papers series (1986-2003) is arranged alphabetically by the title of the paper. It is comprised of papers written or co-written by Professor Gutiérrez. This includes working papers for articles, papers presented at conferences, and drafts of book chapters. Topics include multicultural human services, social work education and research, diversity in social work, HIV/AIDs education, and community organization.
  - Alternative Services and Community Organization: Opportunities and Dilemmas 1986 (Box 1)
  - Choosing to do Participatory Research: An Example and Points to Consider undated (Box 1)
  - Coping with Stressful Life Events: An Empowerment Perspective 1988 (Box 1)
  - Culture and Consciousness in the Chicano Community: An Empowerment Perspective 1988 (Box 1)
  - Developing a Praxis and Research Agenda for Multicultural Human Services Organization 1995 (Box 1)
  - Developing Gender and Ethnically Relevant AIDS Prevention Interventions for High Risk Adolescents 1993 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues on Cultural Diversity and Social Justice in Graduate Social Work 1999 (Box 1)
  - Educating Community Workers for Collaborative Practice: The Michigan Neighborhood AmeriCorps Program 2001 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Identity and Sexual Risk-taking among African Americans Enrolled in an HIV/STD Prevention Intervention 2003 (Box 1)
  - Ethnicity as a Predictor of Sex Role Attitudes 1986 (Box 1)
  - Intersections of Gender, Race, and Ethnicity in Groupwork undated (Box 1)
  - Latinos at Michigan: An Exploratory Study -- A Report Submitted to the Office of Minority Affairs 1990 (Box 1)
  - Multicultural Community Practice Strategies and Intergroup Empowerment 2000 (Box 1)
  - Multicultural Social Work Research: Implications for Social Work Education 2001 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Examination in Social Work: Toward a Model of Empowerment for Social Work 1987 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Evaluation Report: Abstinence Education Demonstration Project 1999 (Box 1)
  - Preparing Students for Macro Practice 1997 (Box 1)
  - Proposal for the Preliminary Examination in Social Work 1986 (Box 1)
  - Replication of a Psychological Rehabilitation Program: A Case Study Analysis of Supported Education 2003 (Box 1)
  - Social Work and Battered Women: The Impact of Feminism on a Profession 1986 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Community Service and Learning at the University of Michigan 2000 (Box 1)
  - Substance Abuse Intervention, Prevention, Rehabilitation and Change undated (Box 1)
  - Women and Empowerment: Issues for Health Education and Promotion 1995 (Box 1)
  - Women's Personal Experiences with Race and Ethnicity 1996 (Box 1)
- Proposals 1995-2006
  The Proposal series (1995-2006) is arranged chronologically. It contains proposals and accompanying narratives submitted to various foundations and companies in application for funding and resources for research and outreach projects.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1995-1998 (Box 1)
  - 1999, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 2000 (Box 1)
  - 2001 (Box 1)
  - 2002, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - 2006 (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1973-2007
  The Topical Files series (1973-2007) is arranged alphabetically. The files in this series cover a number subjects, organizations, projects and research subjects. Items of interest include annual reviews, correspondence, community outreach projects, faculty materials, and a guide to the University of Michigan activities in Metro Detroit.
  - Annual Review 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Annual Review 2002-2003 (Box 2)
  - Annual Review 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Arthur F. Thurnau Professorship 2000 (Box 2)
  - Building Bridges: Participatory Research with Multicultural Community Organizers 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Building Bridges: Participatory Research with Multicultural Community Organizers, Workshop Evaluations 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Building Bridges: Participatory Research with Multicultural Community Organizers --Workshop Planning 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Community Based Initiative Newsletter 2002 (Box 2)
  - Contracts and Agreements 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1995-2000 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2001-2006 (Box 2)
  - Community Outreach Partnership Center (COPC) in Southwest Detroit 2004 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae 2001 (Box 2)
  - Democratic Education through Intergroup Dialogue undated (Box 2)
  - Detroit Initiative 2001 (Box 2)
  - Educating Undergrads for Research and Action in Urban Communities undated (Box 2)
  - Faculty Forum 2000 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Survey on Multi-Cultural Issues in the School of Social Work 1997 (Box 2)
  - GIEU Project: Learning about Globalization and Latino Youth in Three North American Cities undated (Box 2)
  - Guide to University of Michigan Activities in Metropolitan Detroit, c. 1996 (Box 2)
  - Kellogg Global Program on Youth 2004 (Box 2)
  - Latino Faculty Association 1999 (Box 2)
  - MexUsCan Project: Globalization and Latino Youth 2002-2003 (Box 2)
  - Minority Opportunities Committee/ Racism and Gender Issues Task Force 1973-1987 (Box 2)
  - Multicultural Community Based Practice: Strategies and Challenges 2004 (Box 2)
  - Multi-systematic Therapy for Adolescent Females -- Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA) 2000, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical Report 2002 (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical Request 2000 (Box 2)
  - Self-study Report of the Inter-departmental Program in Social Work and Social Science 2004 (Box 2)
  - Social Work Faculty Retreat 2001 (Box 2)
  - Symposium II on University -- Community Partnerships in Detroit Neighborhoods 2001 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan School of Social Work Directory and Photo Roster 2002-2003 (Box 2)